Preliminary Guide to the Peter Storey papers, 1950-2006
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Peter Storey papers 1950-2006
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Storey, Peter John, 1938-
9.0 linear feet Extent: 5000 Items
South African Methodist Church leader and anti-apartheid activist. The Peter Storey Papers contain correspondence, datebooks, articles, lectures, sermons, committee and subject files, clippings, scrapbooks, videotapes, and electronic records. The collection documents Peter Storey's leadership and active involvement in the Methodist Church of Southern Africa, the South African Council of Churches, the Central Methodist Mission in Johannesburg, the Truth and Reconciliation Commission, Gun Free South Africa, and other religious and anti-apartheid groups. Major subjects include Nelson Mandela, Winnie Mandela, urban ministry, crisis intervention, and political violence and elections in South Africa. Materials range in date from circa 1950 to 2006. Acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive.
RL.01260
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In addition, original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Technical Services staff need to produce use copies before contents can be accessed.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Peter Storey papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2006.
Biographical Note
Peter Storey (b. 1938) was schooled in Cape Town, South Africa, spent some time in the South African Navy, and then trained for the Methodist ministry at Rhodes University. Storey pastored churches in Cape Town, and later served as a chaplain to Robben Island prison, where he ministered to Nelson Mandela. After two years in Australia, Storey returned to District Six, a coloured community in Cape Town whose people faced forced removal under apartheid law. Storey was prominent in the fight against these removals, at the same time launching a number of ministries, including The Carpenter's House, Cape Town's first non-racial community center, and founded Dimension, the national newspaper of the Methodist Church, which took an uncompromising anti-apartheid stance under his nine-year editorship.
He was appointed to Johannesburg's Central Methodist Church in 1976, the year of the Soweto uprising, and immediately questioned the all-white nature of the congregation. The following years saw the loss of some 200 white members, but also the creation of the first fully integrated Methodist church in the land. The Central Methodist Mission--as it became known--was a center of protest action against apartheid, often being surrounded and sometimes invaded by government Security Forces.
During this period Storey became Vice President of the South African Council of Churches (SACC) and was elected President of this body in 1981. In this position, he and Bishop Desmond Tutu, who was then General Secretary, steered the SACC through its most controversial and embattled era of anti-apartheid action. This included facing the notorious Eloff Commission of Inquiry into the SACC. His testimony to the Commission has been published under the title Here We Stand.
In 1984 Storey was elected President of the Methodist Church and co-lead an ecumenical delegation to the United Nations and Europe to urge international pressure against the South African Government's forced removal policy. He then became Bishop of the Central District, including Johannesburg and Soweto. He also headed up the Journey to the New Land transformation process, which has redesigned the Methodist Church for its mission in the new South Africa.
Committed to peacemaking, he co-chaired the Wits-Vaal Peace Secretariat, responsible for keeping the peace in the Johannesburg region in the run-up to the first democratic elections and became Patron of the Methodist Order of Peacemakers, which focused on non-violence. He was first chairperson of the Gunfree South Africa movement, and he was a member of President Mandela's Selection Committee for the Truth and Reconciliation Commission.
Storey has received honorary Doctor of Divinity and Doctor of Law degrees. His international ministry has included frequent preaching and lecturing journeys to the United States, Europe, and Australia, and he has addressed many conferences related to the situation in South Africa, the truth and reconciliation process, and world peace.
[Biographical Note adapted from: February 11, 1999 - Rev. Dr. Peter Storey at STH. Boston University School of Theology, March 24, 2003. http://www.bu.edu/sth/news/archive/storey.html]
Collection Overview
The Peter Storey Papers contain correspondence, datebooks, articles, lectures, sermons, committee and subject files, clippings, scrapbooks, videotapes, and electronic records. The collection documents Peter Storey's leadership and active involvement in the Methodist Church of Southern Africa, the South African Council of Churches, the Central Methodist Mission in Johannesburg, the Truth and Reconciliation Commission, Gun Free South Africa, and other religious and anti-apartheid groups. Major subjects include Nelson Mandela, Winnie Mandela, urban ministry, crisis intervention, and political violence and elections in South Africa. Materials range in date from circa 1950 to 2006. Acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive.
Subject Headings
Apartheid -- South Africa; Human Rights Archive (Duke University); Gun Free South Africa (Organization); Human rights -- South Africa; Mandela, Nelson, 1918-; Mandela, Winnie; Methodist Church of Southern Africa; Methodist Church -- South Africa; South Africa. Truth and Reconciliation Commission; South Africa -- Race relations; South Africa -- Politics and government -- 20th century; South African Council of Churches; Storey, Peter John, 1938-; Clippings; Machine-readable records; Videocassettes
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence, 1971-1997 and undated, 1.5 Boxes
  - Correspondence, 1971-1989, (20 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1990-1997 and undated (Box 2)
- Datebooks, 1963-1996, 3 Boxes (Box 2)
  - Datebooks, 1963-1972, (10 items) (Box 3)
  - Datebooks, 1973-1984, (12 items) (Box 4)
  - Datebooks, 1985-1990, (6 items) (Box 5)
  - Datebooks, 1991-1996, (6 items) (Box 6)
- Subject files, circa 1970-2006 and undated, 6.5 Boxes (Box 6)
  - Winnie Mandela saga, 1989-1998, (8 folders) (Box 2)
  - Soweto Happenings, 1976-1978 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - South African Council of Churches (SACC) Ecunews, 1979-1988 (Box 2)
  - God & Caesar material (Box 7)
  - Central Methodist Mission (CMM) quarterly meetings, 1976-1991 (Box 7)
  - Central Methodist Mission Leaders meetings, 1976-1991 (Box 7)
  - Central Methodist Mission staff meetings, 1990 (Box 7)
  - P. W. Botha trial, 1996-1998 (Box 8)
  - Truth and Reconciliation Commission, 1993-1998 (Box 8)
  - Gun Free South Africa, 1992-2001 and undated (Box 8)
  - Lectures on South Africa (Box 9)
  - Evangelism and Bible studies (Box 9)
  - John Wesley -- Methodism (Box 9)
  - National Peace Accord -- Elections (Box 9)
  - Race (Box 9)
  - City Ministry (Box 9)
  - Linda W. Kiester interview, 1986-1987 (Box 9)
  - Kiester notes: Packet 1.1-1.3 (Box 9)
  - Kiester notes: Packet 2.1-2.2 (Box 9)
  - Kiester notes: Packet 2.3 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous interviews (Box 9)
  - Peace, Non-Violent, (3 Folders) (Box 10)
  - Preaching, (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - Addresses and Articles, 1970-1989, (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - Addresses and Articles, 1990-1997, (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - CMM Staff Meetings, 1976-1984, (Folders 1-2 of 3) (Box 10)
  - CMM Staff Meetings, 1976-1984, (Folder 3 of 3) (Box 11)
  - South African Council of Churches (SACC) Presidium, 1976-1981, (3 folders) (Box 11)
  - SACC, Rees, June 16, Other, ELOFF (Box 11)
  - SACC Finance, 1977-1980, (3 folders) (Box 11)
  - Addresses on South Africa (Box 11)
  - Misc. Articles, Conferences, Notes (Box 12)
  - SACC Exec, 1975-1980, (2 folders) (Box 12)
  - SACC Exec, 1981-1990s, (2 folders) (Box 12)
  - Unfiled SAAC (not on CDs) (Box 12)
  - Not on CDs (Box 12)
  - Addresses and Articles, 1998-2006, (3 folders) (Box 12)
- Clippings, 1970-2003, 6.5 Boxes (Box 12)
  - Press clippings (Box 11)
  - Press clippings, 1950-2003 (Box 13)
  - Winnie Mandela clippings (Box 13)
  - Photocopies of newspaper clippings (Box 14)
  - Scrapbook, 1979 (Box 14)
  - Scrapbook, 1980-1984 (Box 14)
  - Photocopies of newspaper clippings (Box 15)
- Videocassettes, circa 1995-2004 and undated, 2 Boxes (Box 15)
  - 'This we can do for justice and for peace' - Tutu & Storey (Box 16)
  - PJS Speaks on TRC in Minneapolis, 1994 (Box 16)
  - 'The Peacemakers' - One day in the life of South Africa's Peace Accord (Box 16)
  - National Peace Accord Peace Song Compilation (Box 16)
  - Talking about God - Where is God in your life? (Box 16)
  - 'Healing the Memories' (USA) Central District Synod, July 1999 (Box 16)
  - When Love Takes You Prisoner Peter Storey - Pasadena, April 29, 2000 (Box 16)
  - Holy Communion - "God's Wholeness for a Broken World" Western North Carolina Conference, 1998 (Box 16)
  - Friday Morning Worship - "Relentless Hospitality of the Holy Spirit" Western North Carolina Conference, 1998 (Box 16)
  - Saturday Morning Worship - "God's Gift of Newness for us All" Western North Carolina Conference, 1998 (Box 16)
  - Discipline-Making Congregations Nashville, 2001 (Box 17)
  - PJS Farewells, SABC i/vs, TRC Willie Mandela Hearing (Box 17)
  - Elections, PJS on Tope Level, Mandela victory speech (Box 17)
  - Gospel Truth and Power - The Church as an Alternative Community University United Methodist Church, February 21, 2003 (Box 17)
  - Sermon by Rev. Dr. Peter Storey University United Methodist Church, February 22, 2003 (Box 17)
  - Lecture 1: "God's Power to Speak the Truth," October 11, 1998 "Gospel Truth and Power" - MTSO Schooler Lectures, 1997 (Box 17)
  - Lecture 2: "Speaking God's Truth to Power," October 12, 1998 "Gospel Truth and Power" - MTSO Schooler Lectures, 1997 (Box 17)
  - The Way of The Powerless Jesus, October 13, 1998 - MTSO Schooler Institute Worship Service, 1997 (Box 17)
  - Resistance & Reconciliation - The Church's Ecumenical Role in Ending Apartheid. The Kathleen & John F. Bricker Memorial Lecture, March 16, 1999 (Box 17)
- Electronic records, circa 2001-2003, 19 Disks (Box 17)
  Series consists of data CDs containing scanned versions of documents found in the Correspondence and Subject Files Series of the Peter Storey Papers. The contents of each disk have been transferred to an archival storage server. The majority of the files are Portable Document Format (PDF), with few JPG and other formats present. Disks 19 and 20 of 21 were not received. A complete list of the file names and directory structure of the disks is available for reference. Please contact the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library for more information.
  - Disk Label: CMM Staff minutes; Central Circuit quarterly min. 1976-1991; Central MM Staff meetings 1976-1989; CMM leaders minutes 1976-1991; Articles & Conferences Notes 1959-1997; NPA - Elections; PJS Addresses & Articles 1970-1989; PJS Addresses & Articles since 23001 (this should read: 1990-May 2000); Prayers by PJ Storey; Preaching, (14 files) (Disk 001, Box 17)
  - Disk Label: ORIGINAL; Articles from Sunday Independent; First Alan Walker lecture; Ministry and Issues; Protest and Resistance; Remembering SA; Sing the Lord's Song in Hostile Land; Things that Make for Peace; God and Caesar Reading Kit, (18 files) (Disk 002, Box 17)
  - Disk Label: Bible Study(s), (1 file) (Disk 003, Box 17)
  - Disk Label: Peace (aaa01164); Evangelism; Peace and Non-violence (Damaged), (3 files) (Disk 004, Box 17)
  - Disk Label: Peace and Non-Violence (Disk 005, Box 17)
    The contents of Disk 005 could not be accessed.
  - Disk Label: Poor, (1 file) (Disk 006, Box 17)
  - Disk Label: SACC 1982; Eloff Commission; JC Rees; R...; Venola; Naribia; Mokena; Race, (2 files) (Disk 007, Box 17)
  - Disk Label: City; SACC Exec meetings 1972-1980, (2 files) (Disk 008, Box 17)
  - Disk Label: Praesidium; SACC 1977-1980; SACC Finance Committee 1978-1982, (2 files) (Disk 009, Box 17)
  - Disk Label: June 16, 1976; Roelotse - Mokoena; SACC Exe Meetings 1981-1982 plus audits, (3 files) (Disk 010, Box 17)
  - Disk Label: Asingeni - Chetty; Discussion on Wesley; Misc Interview et al (DAMAGED); Miscellaneous: Some Eloff PJS, Some SACC, Letter to PM, Meeting with Botha 1980, Invite to O...; Radio Talks July 1996; SACC Exec Meetings (DAMAGED), (5 files) (Disk 011, Box 17)
    One file (SACC Exec meetings 1977-81.pdf) could not be transferred to the storage server.
  - Disk Label: JCR - PJS Resignation; SACC 1981; Wesley & Methodism, (3 files) (Disk 012, Box 17)
  - Disk Label: GFSA, (139 files) (Disk 013, Box 17)
  - Disk Label: Misc.; Interview part one, (1 file) (Disk 014, Box 17)
  - Disk Label: Soweto; Misc.; Lectures on SA, (15 files) (Disk 015, Box 17)
  - Disk Label: Truth and Reconciliation Commission; W. Mandela; Botha, (180 files) (Disk 016, Box 17)
  - Disk Label: Correspondence, 1971-1987, (599 files) (Disk 017, Box 17)
  - Disk Label: Correspondence, 1988-1997 and undated, (238 files) (Disk 018, Box 17)
  - Disk Label: Our Ancestors, (84 files) (Disk 021, Box 17)